<states><state id="1" name="New South Wales" ><region id="19" name="Canberra District" blurb="" images="" climate="The region has one of the strongest Continental climates in Australia, with a high diurnal temperature range." date="The first vines were planted in 1971." soil="Soils are typically brownish, shallow clay loams, often overlying shale or clay, with a pH ranging from neutral to mildly acidic." fact="The Canberra District wine region incorporates the majority of vineyard developments in the northern part of the Australian Capital Territory and the adjoining area of New South Wales." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Some notably elegant wines are produced, with a good structure and complexity that reflects its cooler aspects." varietal2="Riesling" varietaltext2="The majority are made in a crisp, gently toasty, dry style, with sweeter styles less favoured. However, in the warmer years, more tropical characteristics appear. Modest yields ensure that the wines age well in bottle for up to a decade." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="Cabernet's overall weight and extract varies from light, leafy and minty to rich, concentrated and chocolatey." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="Wineries are producing spectacularly good examples that are redolent of spice, black cherry and liquorice." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="20" name="Cowra" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate is of Continental nature, with moderate rainfall. Described as moderately acidic, the soils are brownish loamy sand to clay loam on the surface, with red clay subsoils." date="First vines planted in 1973, followed by significant expansion in the 1990s." soil="The soils are brownish loamy sand to clay loam on the surface, with red clay subsoils. They are moderately acidic and vary from low to moderately fertile." fact="Cowra wine region is located in the NSW Central Ranges, approximately 300 metres above sea level." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="In younger wines, yellow peach and ripe fig flavours tend to dominate and a degree of French oak influence is frequently encountered. However, some older wines of this variety are demonstrating a capacity to develop into ultra-rich, honey and buttered toast styles." varietal2="Shiraz" varietaltext2="With increased age of vines in the area, the red wines are starting to show depth of flavour and colour. Shiraz has performed extremely well, with the wines showing ripe fruit characters as well as some earthy and peppery notes." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon and Merlot" varietaltext3="These show the full expression of ripe fruit characteristics of dark berries, chocolate and eucalypt. The tannins are smooth and carry the fruit of the wine well. They are renowned for their easy drinking and approachability." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="21" name="Gundagai " blurb="" images="" climate="The region experiences warm to hot in temperatures with an even year-round rainfall." date="The McWilliam family established the successful Markview vineyard at Junee in 1877, since 1995 there has been a flurry of plantings." soil="The main soil types are red earth and red podsols." fact="It is an undulating region, with altitude varying between 200 and 300 metres." varietal1="Shiraz" varietaltext1="These are wines of medium to full body, showing berry and earth characters on the nose and palate and distinctly reminiscent of the Hilltops region to the north-west." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="These are well-coloured, berry-flavoured reds of medium to full body. Again, there is a resemblance to the Cabernets of the Hilltops region." varietal3="Chardonnay" varietaltext3="The region makes both unwooded and wooded Chardonnay styles. Melon, stone fruit, lime and citrus characters dominate. The Chardonnays are surprisingly elegant and lend themselves to subtle oak handling." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="22" name="Hastings River" blurb="" images="" climate="This region is uncompromisingly warm, with high summer humidity and high rainfall." date="The Hastings River has a viticulture and winemaking history dating back to 1837." soil="The soils vary greatly in fertility, depth and drainage capacity, spanning rich free-draining alluvial and red volcanic soils, and running from sandy through to heavy, water-resistant yellow clay; some are deep, while others overlie gravel or limestone." fact="The best vintages are the driest; those in which the late summer rains are below average." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="It lends itself to manipulation in the winery and to the use of oak to add complexity and depth.  As might be expected, it matures relatively quickly but the wines from drier vintages can hold their peak for several years." varietal2="Semillon" varietaltext2="The thin skins and large berries of Semillon are especially vulnerable to the effects of vintage rain.  Early picking is important to ensure a high quality wine." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon/Merlot" varietaltext3="These varieties are soft and quite fleshy, with abundant berry and earth flavours. Merlot, too, can be successfully made as a single varietal, though it is sometimes seen as a cross-regional blend." varietal4="Chambourcin" varietaltext4="Intensely purple in colour, the flavour of Chambourcin is pronounced.  In its youth, it falls into the black cherry and plum range with occasional slight spicy and gamey overlays.  As a young, fresh wine it is among the best examples of hybrids produced anywhere in the world." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="23" name="Hilltops" blurb="" images="" climate="The region has a Continental climate, with the higher altitude ensuring an even and lengthy ripening period. While substantial rainfall occurs in the growing season, most rainfall is in spring." date="There appear to have been some wineries in the Hilltops region, run by settlers from the Dalmatian coast of Croatia, towards the end of the 19th century." soil="The soils are rich and deep; typically dark red granite clays impregnated with basalt. They are free draining, supporting strong vine growth." fact="" varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="For such a warm area, the Chardonnays are surprisingly lean and elegant, with citrus and melon flavours merging into stony/mineral characteristics. They lend themselves to subtle oak handling and give every impression they will age with grace for five years." varietal2="Semillon" varietaltext2="They are powerful and carry excellent mid-palate weight." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="It produces a characteristic style and some fine wines are made here from this grape." varietal4="Verdelho" varietaltext4="Verdelho ripens early in the harvest and is made using the same methods as Semillon except that it is usually picked riper. It goes into bottle early and is usually at its best in the year or two after it is made, when it shows ripe, tropical flavours." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="24" name="Hunter Valley" blurb="" images="" climate="The Hunter Valley is warm, even hot. In addition to hot days, the Hunter Valley has relatively warm nights when the physiological processes that ripen fruit can continue." date="The Hunter Valley is Australia's oldest producing wine region, with vines first planted in the 1820's, with some of the oldest vine stock in the world." soil="Soils vary from sandy alluvial flats to red clay loams &amp; chocolate brown podsols. " fact="The region's aged Hunter Valley Semillons are widely considered a world benchmark style." varietal1="Semillon" varietaltext1="A world benchmark wine, Hunter Valley Semillon is the stellar white variety in the region. Semillon is at its delicate best when picked early to make a wine of ten to 11.5% alcohol and almost invariably has ripe flavours at low sugar concentrations. This is the style of wine that best responds to bottle age, during which it develops outstanding lemon curd and toasty complexity and becomes barely recognisable from its demure beginning." varietal2="Chardonnay" varietaltext2="Virtually every winery in the region produces a Chardonnay with three different styles produced. The first is the traditional style with a rich peachy flavour, new oak &amp; a full body; the second is an earlier picked tighter style, lighter in body &amp; a little higher in acidity; the third is an unoaked or lightly oaked chardonnay that has been fermented in stainless steel." varietal3="Verdelho" varietaltext3="Verdelho ripens early in the harvest, so there's usually little difficulty in getting very ripe flavours and a full body. Verdelho is made using the same methods as Semillon, with the exception that it's usually picked somewhat riper. It goes into bottle early and is usually at its best in the year or two after it's made, when it shows ripe, tropical flavours." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="Young Hunter Valley Shiraz is a medium bodied wine showing red and dark berries, spices and plenty of soft tannin. It is quite deceptive, as the best can age for a considerable time, more than their constitution often suggests." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="25" name="Mudgee" blurb="" images="" climate="Frosts and cold nights delay budburst; rainfall and humidity are low; sunshine hours are great; and irrigation is essential on some but the most favoured sites." date="Viticulture commenced in 1858." soil="The brownish coloured soils are typical of those found through the majority of the wine regions of eastern Australia; slightly acidic or sandy loam over neutral clay subsoils, but both topsoil and subsoil have the advantage of being quite well drained." fact="Situated on the western slopes of the Great Dividing Range, Mudgee has some of the highest vineyards in Australia." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The flavours are usually in the peach, melon, fig spectrum but often citrus and grapefruit characteristics emerge, particularly where the maker employs barrel-ferment techniques.  The wines show their best varietal character in the second and third years but do go on to develop into rich and honeyed regional styles over a much longer timeframe." varietal2="Semillon" varietaltext2="Has the capacity to age gloriously in bottle for up to 20 years. Mudgee Semillon can be picked at low sugar levels and display grassy, nutty characters with great length of flavour." varietal3="Riesling" varietaltext3="Vineyard site selection is paramount, with elevation and soil playing an important role. Off dry styles through to bone dry have great fruit intensity and purity, with citrus and orange blossom characters." varietal4="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext4="The generous flavours reflect the warm climate; a melange of tastes of red berry, dark chocolate and, sometimes, eucalypt and peppermint.  The tannins are almost invariably pronounced but are not excessively astringent, for they are balanced by the generosity of the fruit." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="26" name="New England Australia" blurb="" images="" climate="Topographical diversity and varying altitude offer a wide range of climate options suitable for viticulture." date="Viticulture initially flourished in the 1880s. In 1882 it was described as &quot;one of the foremost wine producing regions in the colonies&quot; in the Sydney Daily Mail." soil="The region is the only place in Australia where terra rossa soils exist at high altitude." fact="Warm days and cool nights allow slow ripening and well developed fruit flavours." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The New England region offers some very elegant and well balanced Chardonnays with excellent varietal definition.  These wines display generous aromas of stone fruit, citrus and tropical fruit. The careful use of oak allows integration with the fruit." varietal2="Riesling" varietaltext2="Fragrant floral characters, exotic and citrus fruit round out the aromatics of these lively wines.  The rich fruit flavours and balanced acidity are hallmarks of the Rieslings from the region." varietal3="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext3="The region's Sauvignon Blanc is enhanced with aromas of gooseberry, lemon and passionfruit characteristics.  The wines are elegantly structured." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="The delicate aromas of plum, red berries and white pepper are frequently found in the Shiraz from the region.  Soft, velvety tannin structures enhance the mouth-feel and roundness on the palate." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="27" name="Orange" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate has mild to warm mid-summer mean temperatures and cool to very cool nights during the growing season." date="Orange has long been an important orchard area. Vines were first planted commercially in 1980." soil="The undulating countryside is of fundamental importance in determining site selection as the soils vary widely. High altitude imparts unique characteristics." fact="" varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The style is a neat balance between fleshy, rich, quick developing warm climate Chardonnay and the ultra-fine, slow developing, citrus and cashew style of cooler climates." varietal2="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext2="The more vigorous soils also produce fruit with an herbaceous character that complements the strong fruit flavours." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon/Merlot" varietaltext3="The flavours run through the herbaceous and earthy spectrum with dark berry sweetness. They are of medium weight and body and have fine tannins. They can also be very effectively blended with wines from warmer regions such as Mudgee, the Hunter Valley and Cowra." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="This is a recently planted variety showing true varietal flavours and exceptional colour. As in many other regions of Australia, Shiraz is the most widely planted variety in Orange." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="28" name="Perricoota" blurb="" images="" climate="Perricoota enjoys many long hours of regular sunshine, which helps winemakers to produce wines that are full in flavour and structure, but with a softer and approachable style." date="The region, which takes its name from a grazing property established in 1840, achieved Geographical Indication status in 1999." soil="Perricoota has a typical Australian riverine landscape of flat terrain with remnants of river red gum forests. Its soils, of moderate acidity tending to alkalinity at depth, are generally red clay loams of good texture with fair to good moisture holding capacity." fact="Perricoota is two hours' drive from Melbourne and eight hours' from Sydney." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The region produces some outstanding Chardonnay wines, exhibiting full and balanced flavour suitable for early drinking" varietal2="Semillon" varietaltext2="Wines of typical lemony character showing good acidity. Perhaps Semillon is even more suited to the region than Chardonnay, but only time will tell." varietal3="Shiraz" varietaltext3="These are wines of good colour, showing supple medium weight palates of berry flavour, sometimes with a little liquorice complexity." varietal4="Cabernet" varietaltext4="The Cabernet wines typically have excellent colour and are generously flavoured and well structured wines. Good examples are ideal cellaring candidates." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="29" name="Riverina" blurb="" images="" climate="Autumn conditions favour the onset and spread of the fungus Botrytis Cinerea. The higher humidity late in the season allows Botrytis or &quot;Noble Rot&quot; development to occur after the picking of most of the red and white varieties." date="Viticulture can be traced from 1912 and the arrival of John James McWilliam.	 	" soil="A warm, dry environment and secure water supplies make it a reliable grape producing region." fact="The Riverina is a very important wine region. It has achieved international acclaim for its sweet, botrytis-affected white wines." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Careful use of oak produces a wine of pleasant varietal flavour, weight and style." varietal2="Semillon" varietaltext2="These days specially selected blocks of Semillon grapes are left on the vine for up to two months after maturity. As a consequence if the conditions are favourable, Botrytis Cinerea attacks the grapes, evaporating the water content of their juice and concentrating both its sugar and acid. The resultant wine is a luscious Sauternes-style dessert win, the regions outstanding specialty." varietal3="Red Wines" varietaltext3="The quality of wine from this region improved significantly during the last decade of the 20th century." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="30" name="Shoalhaven Coast" blurb="" images="" climate="Growing season temperatures are quite warm, though extremely high summer temperatures are uncommon due to the strong influence of the Pacific Ocean." date="Viticulture commenced in the 1970s, ebfore which the region was famous for its beaches." soil="Most soils are red and brown earths well suited to viticulture." fact="Chief viticultural hazard is rainfall during harvest, while high humidity can result in downy/powdery mildew and Botrytis." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Chardonnay is planted up and down the length of the Shoalhaven Coast. It produces a pleasant, mid-weight wine with gentle peachy fruit flavours and a soft finish." varietal2="Shiraz and Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="These are paired because they are so often blended and because, either as single varietal wines or as blends, they produce soft, faintly earthy wines without having an especially distinctive varietal character. With appropriate winery techniques, these are fresh, well-balanced, light-to medium-bodied wines best consumed while young." varietal3="Chambourcin" varietaltext3="Chambourcin constitutes the majority of the other red plantings. The vibrant colour and fresh plum fruit aroma and flavour of the wine are best enjoyed while it is young; sometimes a touch of new oak is introduced to increase the balance, complexity and length of the wine." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="31" name="Southern Highlands" blurb="" images="" climate="Generally the region is cool, moist and slightly humid, and can be characterised as having a moderately Continental climate with mild summers and cool winters." date="Modern-day viticulture commenced in the 1980s." soil="Principal viticultural soils are derived from basalt and shale." fact="The region forms part of the Great Dividing Range, south-west of Sydney." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Yet another of Australia's cooler Chardonnay areas, the region makes both unwooded and wooded styles. Melon, lime and citrus characters dominate, sometimes with a touch of green apple. Oak handling is light and skilful; acidity is generally good, auguring well for ageing." varietal2="Riesling" varietaltext2="With floral citrus complexities in young wines and touches of honey and toast in older wines." varietal3="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext3="These wines are very much in the general run of good cool-area Australian Sauvignon Blanc; light, smoky, grassy traits on nose and palate with good acidity." varietal4="Cabernet Sauvignon and Blends" varietaltext4="The Southern Highlands is an area where Cabernet Sauvignon and its related varieties perform better in warmer years. It is producing medium-bodied wines showing light berry and briar characteristics, mostly from young vines." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="32" name="Tumbarumba" blurb="" images="" climate="There are a number of factors that affect the region's climate: high sunshine hours with brilliant light, cold summer nights and a late start to the growing season." date="Viticulture commenced in 1982." soil="Soils are granular and derived from decomposed granite and basalt." fact="The Tumbarumba region is in the Snowy Mountains, a part of the Australian Alps which feature the nation's highest peak, Mount Kosciusko." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Chardonnay can be distinguished by crisp melon, citrus and fig fruit in the classic style of a cool climate wine." varietal2="Sparkling Wines" varietaltext2="Employing a classic blend of Chardonnay, Pinot Noir and Pinot Meunier but also utilising a multiplicity of other regional sources." varietal3="Pinot Noir" varietaltext3="The region has the capacity to produce very stylish Pinot Noir with a clear varietal character." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region></state><state id="2" name="Queensland" ><region id="33" name="Granite Belt" blurb="" images="" climate="Sub zero winter nights, spring frosts, cold nights at the beginning and end of the season, relatively low humidity, peak summer temperatures moderated by sub-tropical monsoon influences and intermittent heavy late season rainfall contribute to the unusual climate in Granite Belt." date="Grapes were first planted in the Granite Belt in the 1870s." soil="Permian sedimentary rocks, intrusive granites and extensive Tertiary basalts." fact="Areas within the region rise to 1020 metres above sea level, making the vineyards among Australia's highest." varietal1="Verdelho" varietaltext1="This variety appears to be well suited to the warmer days and cool night the region offers. Wines are often aromatic, with herbaceous and tropical fruit flavours." varietal2="Chardonnay" varietaltext2="The wine tends to be soft but have pleasant and clear varietal character in a nectarine and melon spectrum. Many wineries produce both oaked and unoaked Chardonnay to good effect." varietal3="Viognier" varietaltext3="These wines are often dry, with a fruity, citrus palate. Small quantities of Viognier may be added to Shiraz to give lightness, delicacy and perfume to the red wine." varietal4="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext4="Like Shiraz, this wine is full, dark and rich in flavour. Cassis, red berry and sweet fruit flavours predominate, attesting to the warm climate and the use of rich, vanillin oak." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="34" name="South Burnett" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate can be classed as sub-tropical and combines mild winters and warm summers, making it similar to the Hunter Valley." date="The South Burnett region has a modern history of viticulture dating back to 1993." soil="There is a diverse range of soils, described in ascending order as light sands, a variety of light clay red soils through to brown and black clays. The red, brown and black soils are of moderate to high fertility, and all have a pH level suited to viticulture." fact="The district is less than three hours from Brisbane and two hours from the Sunshine coast." varietal1="Verdelho" varietaltext1="This variety appears to be well suited to warmer days and cool night. Wines are often aromatic, with herbaceous and tropical fruit flavours." varietal2="Chardonnay" varietaltext2="The wine tends to be soft with pleasant and clear varietal character in a nectarine and melon spectrum. The use of quality oak and modern winemaking practices has produced many wines with good complexity and structure." varietal3="Semillon" varietaltext3="The style of the Semillon is relatively quick to develop. It provides a distinctive varietal flavour, with some citrus and herb characters." varietal4="Cabernet Sauvignon and Merlot" varietaltext4="This region is producing medium bodied wines with soft, sweet berry flavours. As the vines age, more extract and structure can be expected when vintage conditions are favourable." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region></state><state id="3" name="Victoria" ><region id="37" name="Alpine Valleys" blurb="" images="" climate="The climatic conditions encourage a long, moderate growing period, producing high-quality grapes." date="" soil="Soils in the region have good structure, with above-average fertility. " fact="The Alpine Valley region is located in a pristine alpine environment, which includes the major ski fields in Victoria." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Produced for sparkling and table wine, the style depends in part on the altitude which it is grown. For use as a sparkling wine, the grapes will usually come from higher altitude vineyards. These wines are growing in reputation." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon and Shiraz" varietaltext2="Full-bodied, earthy red wines are produced at lower altitudes. These wines can be rustic, savoury and full flavoured." varietal3="Merlot" varietaltext3="This is a variety that is planted primarily in vineyards of higher elevation. The elevation gives these wines a sense of elegance and refinement." varietal4="Others" varietaltext4="In common with its neighbour, King Valley, this region is increasing its plantings of interesting Italian varietals such as Sangiovese, Barbera, Nebbiolo and Marzemino." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="38" name="Beechworth" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate is linked to altitude, with a wide range in heat degree summations between the lower and higher elevations. The picturesque township is etched precariously on a steep hillside, with streets plunging at precipitous and unexpected angles." date="The town of Beechworth as founded in 1853 during the gold rush." soil="Two major soil types in the region - Ordovician sandstone, mudstone and shale and the Devonian granites with their more intrusive, igneous nature." fact="The first vines were planted in the region in 1856 by a Mr Rochlitz, who had obtained various varieties from Adelaide." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="At the highest elevations, the grapes will most likely be used for sparkling wine, while richer table wines will come from the lowest elevations." varietal2="Pinot Noir" varietaltext2="The variety has the greatest chance of success at elevations such as Beechworth and above, i.e. 550 metres (1,804 feet) and higher. The climate at lower levels is too warm for the variety to express itself typically." varietal3="Shiraz" varietaltext3="This grape has already made its mark with the rich but elegant styles. It seems certain to provide stylish wines at intermediate altitudes, with more traditional varieties at lower levels." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="39" name="Bendigo" blurb="" images="" climate="There is some variation in mesoclimatic conditions due to elevation, slope and aspect, from the foothills of the central highlands to the warmer undulating plains west and north of Bendigo." date="Vines have been planted in the Bendigo region since 1856, just after the start of the Gold Rush." soil="Soils are loamy sand to clay loam soils over a stony clay base." fact="Bendigo is situated in central Victoria and has a Mediterranean climate, with dry summers and wet winters." varietal1="White Wines" varietaltext1="Chardonnay can be successfully grown and made in almost any combination of climate and soil." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="The wines have great depth of colour, a rich texture with abundant tannins, and fruit flavours ranging from faintly tobacco and herbaceous (in the coolest years) through to the far more common blackberry and black currant flavours. The intensity of the trademark regional eucalypt-peppermint character varies from vintage to vintage and from wine to wine but it is seldom entirely absent. The wines are long-lived with excellent cellaring potential." varietal3="Shiraz" varietaltext3="The colour is deep and the wine has a voluptuous, mouth-filling flavour and texture. Red berries and cherries are supported by more exotic pepper and spice flavours. Like the Cabernet Sauvignon the wines are long-lived with excellent cellaring potential." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="40" name="Geelong" blurb="" images="" climate="The region's climate is cool, providing an extended ripening period. The majority of the area is strongly influenced by the moderating effect of the surrounding water of Port Philip Bay or Bass Strait." date="In 1845, Swiss immigrant vignerons produced Victoria's first commercial vintage in Geelong." soil="The principal soil type is the commonly encountered red-brown clay loam over a hard clay base. A second soil type is also found, that of Biscay; black cracking clay, which forms a finely cracked surface crust. " fact="Geelong was the largest grape-growing region in Victoria in the 1800s. However, from the 1870s when phylloxera was discovered in some vines, there was a winemaking hiatus of nearly 100 years." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Chardonnay has shown it can produce a wine of exceptional strength and complexity. It can also be made in a simpler and more easily accessible form on the Bellarine Peninsula." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="The area is capable of producing concentrated, powerful and long-lived Cabernets with, at their best, intense blackcurrant characteristics." varietal3="Pinot Noir" varietaltext3="The styles of the wine are predictably very different from producer to producer, reflecting differing winemaking techniques and philosophies. The wines commonly express plums, tobacco, violets, strawberries and truffles." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="Geelong Shiraz wines, in favourable years, have strength, depth of colour, bouquet and flavour. While the wines sometimes show pepper and spice overtones, more often than not they rely on potent dark cherry fruit with persistent tannins providing structure and longevity." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="41" name="Gippsland" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate is influenced by the weather systems moving across the south of the continent from the west to the east." date="Modern-day viticulture commenced in the 1970s." soil="Soils vary from deep sandy clay loams to gravelly sandy loams." fact="The Gippsland wine covers a large area extending from the NSW / Victorian border, along the coast to Wonthaggi just below Melbourne, then west to the edge of the Great Dividing Range." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="In East Gippsland, low yields produce wines of exceptional flavour, structure and overall impact. Structured and balanced Chardonnay is made in West Gippsland, with finer and more elegant versions in South Gippsland." varietal2="Pinot Noir" varietaltext2="Rich and rustic in East and West Gippsland. South Gippsland Pinot Noir is fine and elegant, but with deceptive length and intensity." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon and Merlot" varietaltext3="Medium-bodied, the wines do best in warmer vintages." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="42" name="Glenrowan" blurb="" images="" climate="Glenrowan enjoys a warm climate similar to nearby Rutherglen." date="One of Victoria's most historic wine regions, with production dating back to 1870." soil="The Warby Ranges are the predominant geological formation in the region. Soils range from deep red or loamy clay to silty sands." fact="Early success came from production of fortified wine." varietal1="Shiraz" varietaltext1="The earthy berry-flavoured Shiraz reds of Glenrowan are wines of stature and among the bigger Australian Shiraz styles, worthy of cellaring for many years." varietal2="Fortifieds" varietaltext2="Muscats and Tokays vie with those from the nearby Rutherglen region for primacy among Australia's dessert wine styles." varietal3="" varietaltext3="" varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="43" name="Goulburn Valley" blurb="" images="" climate="The region has a typical inland valley-floor climate, with the Goulburn River being the predominant topographical feature influencing the local terroir." date="The Goulburn Valley has a detailed history dating back to first vineyard plantings in 1860." soil="The soils vary widely, falling into three principal groups. There are the usual red and brown sandy clay loams of south-eastern Australia, plus yellow-brown clay loams and gritty, gravelly quartzose sands laid down by the Goulburn River." fact="The history of the Goulburn Valley is closely linked to the historic Tahbilk winery. The &quot;old cellars&quot; at Tahbilk were completed at the end of the 1860s and the &quot;new cellar&quot;, sitting underneath the immaculately preserved wooden winery buildings, commenced in 1875." varietal1="Shiraz" varietaltext1="The wines present ripe, rich fruit overtones when young and age to reveal darker fruits, with hints of pepper, dark chocolate, soft supple leather and earth." varietal2="Marsanne" varietaltext2="Lemon-accented, the oaked styles gain intensity and richness with age. Unoaked, the wine is delicate in its youth and can be long-lived. As these wines age, they build the honeysuckle bouquet and taste that typifies the variety." varietal3="Riesling" varietaltext3="Despite being a region with a warmer climate, the region can produce excellent Riesling. The wines have considerable weight, with lime and tropical fruit aromas and flavours. Despite their early appeal, the wines also have the capacity to age attractively over the medium term." varietal4="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext4="Cabernet Sauvignon grew in importance to the region as the variety become more popular in the 1970s and 1980s. Goulburn Valley produces a style that has ripe, warm, earthy, chocolate-accented flavours." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="44" name="Grampians" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate of the region is Mediterranean and the proximity to the Southern Ocean (between 100 -200 kilometres) provides a cooling influence during summer." date="Vineyards were first planted in 1867 and included grape varieties so rare that several have defied all attempts at identification and are, in all probability, the sole surviving examples in the world." soil="There are two principal soil types; acidic grey and grey-brown loamy sands and clay loam soils and hard yellow soil with structured clay subsoils." fact="Just two hours' drive west from Melbourne, the landscape of the Grampians wine region is renowned for its natural beauty." varietal1="Riesling" varietaltext1="The style shows tropical lime juice aroma and flavour in the warmer years, with reserved, toasty wines in the cooler vintages." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="Often blended with Shiraz (and other varieties), Cabernet Sauvignon performs well in adverse conditions. Blackcurrant, blackberry and even raspberry flavours dominate without threatening the elegant style of the wine." varietal3="Shiraz" varietaltext3="The style ranges from silky smooth wines with red cherry and plum flavours through to strikingly concentrated wines, redolent with spice, pepper, liquorice and game. There is a common thread to these wines in their elegance and fine tannins, no doubt deriving from the cool conditions under which the grapes have ripened. " varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="45" name="Heathcote" blurb="" images="" climate="The region's climate and soil are influenced by the Mt Carmel Range, which provides a natural tunnel for prevailing south to south-east winds that blow throughout the growing season." date="The region was largely used for sheep grazing and it has only been since the 1960s that it has developed into a wine production area." soil="The soil of the Mt Carmel Range is textured red calcareous sodic clay, known as Cambrian Greenstone." fact="Heathcote is located in central Victoria, nestled between the Goulburn Valley and Bendigo regions." varietal1="Shiraz" varietaltext1="It is deep, rich and velvety, with cascades of dark cherry plum and sweetly spicy fruit. The ripe but fine tannins give texture, sustaining length and a superb ability to age." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="The Cabernet Sauvignon style is rich and generous, with blackberry aromatics and flavours. Some of the classic central Victorian eucalypt-mint character is present in some vintages." varietal3="" varietaltext3="" varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="46" name="Henty" blurb="" images="" climate="This is one of the coolest of the wine growing regions on the Australian mainland, producing quality wines from grapes grown in quite cold temperatures." date="Viticulture was pioneered in Henty in 1964 by Karl Seppelt, who accurately conceived it as an ideal cool region for the production of sparkling and delicate, aromatic wines." soil="The vineyards are most widely planted on older Basalt soils: weathered basalt with gravelly loam topsoil overlying red clay." fact="The Henty wine region covers a large area of Victoria and extends from the Hopkins River across to the South Australian border. The region is situated to the east of South Australia's Coonawarra." varietal1="Riesling" varietaltext1="Fine, intense and gently lime-accented wines gradually assume toastier characteristics as they develop in bottle over a decade or more, but they do not lose their trademark elegance." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="The vintage conditions have to be favourable due to the cool climate, but when they are Cabernet is produced with striking similarities to the wines from the Haut Medoc in Bordeaux. The prominent characters of the wines are cassis, cedar and cigar box." varietal3="Meunier" varietaltext3="Meunier account for more than half the total plantings and are largely directed to Seppelt sparkling wine-making." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="47" name="King Valley" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate changes progressively and significantly from lower northern to higher southern elevations, with a progressive increase in rainfall and a decrease in heat summations." date="The region planted its first vines in the late 1800s." soil="Soil types vary significantly, changing with altitude, slope and site characteristics. Deep red clay loams abound, at times veering more to grey or brown in colour but having the same structure." fact="Encompassing the watershed of the King Rive, King Valley has extremely varied terrain and is one of the highest wine grape growing areas in Australia." varietal1="Sangiovese" varietaltext1="Has been shown to be perfectly suited to the region's cool climate, with the wines developing distinctive varietal characteristics." varietal2="Pinot Gris / Grigio" varietaltext2="Both the Gris and Grigio style are produced in the valley.  The Grigio wines boast fresh aromas of citrus and pear, with a palate of distinct savoury characters and a crisp finish thanks to the cool climate fruit. The French Gris style on the other hand is richer on the palate with an exquisite tang of tropical acids." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="Ripening readily, the Cabernet Sauvignon, the resultant wines are soft but flavoursome with flavours are in the sweet berry spectrum, with just a hint of mint and more herbaceous notes." varietal4="Sparkling Wines" varietaltext4="Chardonnay and Pinot Noir are principally utilised by many of Australia's leading sparkling winemakers as blend components." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="48" name="Macedon Ranges" blurb="" images="" climate="Australia's coolest wine region on the mainland. The Macedon Ranges climate is extremely cold in its windswept south-east and very cold in its north-west." date="The regions first vineyards were planted in the mid-1880s." soil="The majority of the soils are relatively skeletal mountain soils, most typically granitic sandy loams which further restrict yields." fact="Only an hour north-west of Melbourne, the Macedon Ranges features towns such as Daylesford and Hepburn Springs which include the largest concentration of naturally occurring mineral springs in Australia." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Fine, elegant and potentially long lived wines often fuller flavoured styles with great complexity." varietal2="Riesling" varietaltext2="Fine, intense, lime juice aroma and flavour that ages wonderfully well." varietal3="Pinot Noir" varietaltext3="Fine and lighter bodied in style in the cooler vintages, more robust and fuller bodied in warmer years." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="Due to the regions climate, the wines are genuinely cool climate in style. Striking pepper, spice, liquorice and black cherry aromas are hallmarks of the region." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="49" name="Mornington Peninsula" blurb="" images="" climate="Surrounded by Bass Strait, Port Phillip Bay and Western Port Bay, the Mornington Peninsula is one of Australia's true maritime wine regions." date="First planted in 1886, the region experienced a viticultural renaissance in the early 1970s." soil="There are four principal soil types. Hard mottled yellow duplex soils with a very distinct break marked by a thin, acid cement/sand pan between the surface soil and the underlying friable, well-drained clay are to be found in the Dromana area. Around Red Hill and Main Ridge, red soils of volcanic origin (kraznozems) predominate; these are very deep and fertile. In the Merricks area there are brown duplex soils, while much sandier soils are in evidence at Moorooduc." fact="The Mornington Peninsula landscape is open, with gently undulating hills, rolling green pastures and tranquil vineyards.  Vines thrive in sheltered undulating valleys with plentiful winter/spring rainfall." varietal1="Pinot Noir" varietaltext1="From cherry and raspberry flavours with soft tannins in the higher areas to more tannic, elegant yet assertive wines with plum fruit in the warmer areas." varietal2="Chardonnay" varietaltext2="The Mornington Peninsula provides a diverse range of micro climates that are perfectly matched to the production of high quality chardonnay. Chardonnay benefits from the extraordinary natural acidity that the cool Mornington Peninsula climate can produce." varietal3="Pinot Gris and Grigio" varietaltext3="Pinot Gris produces soft, evocatively perfumed wines of surprising substance and complexity. Two distinct styles are made - the voluptuous 'Gris' and the svelte 'Grigio' which Italian wine producers tend to pick before full ripeness." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="50" name="Murray Darling" blurb="" images="" climate="The region faces long, hot sunshine hours with negligible growing season rainfall, making irrigation essential." date="The first grape vines were planted in the region in 1888, before this the region was a virtual desert before irrigation transformed it in the late 1800s." soil="The region's soil is unique to the Murray River and is known as calcareous earth." fact="The Murray Darling region is located along the Murray River in North West Victoria and Western New South Wales." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The wines have a fruity softness and generosity." varietal2="Shiraz and Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="The red wine boom saw the plantings of these varieties increase dramatically. The wines have plenty of soft, sweet fruit, making them ideal for drinking at one to two years of age." varietal3="Viognier" varietaltext3="The wines have a fruity softness and generosity." varietal4="Chardonnay" varietaltext4="A table wine that is easily blended and used in generic cask wine. A light and fragrant white which can display tropical fruit characteristics." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="51" name="Pyrenees" blurb="" images="" climate="Temperate, dry climate, the inland location gives rise to low midsummer relative humidity and to substantial diurnal temperature ranges in spring and early summer. Premium full-bodied red wine producing region." date="" soil="The soils are the common grey-brown and brown loamy sands and sandy loams, though tending to be heavy.  They are improved by the addition of gypsum and lime. " fact="A southern extension of the Great Dividing Range, the Pyrenees foothills and ranges create a remarkable diversity of microclimates." varietal1="Shiraz" varietaltext1="Sweet and rich fruit flavours with red/black cherry and dark chocolate the dominant flavours. Pepper and spice occasionally appear alongside strong, supple tannins that ensure these wines have good ageing potential." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="The wines produced from Cabernet Sauvignon can possess a sumptuously rich mid palate, with flavours running from eucalypt mint through to black currant as well as the earthy characters that develop during maturation." varietal3="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext3="Sauvignon Blanc in the cooler years is showing distinctive varietal character." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="52" name="Rutherglen" blurb="" images="" climate="The region's climate is strongly Continental, with very hot summer days and cold nights." date="Winemaking has been a family tradition in Rutherglen since the 1850s, since vines came to Rutherglen along with the Gold Rush." soil="The great fortified wines for which the region is famous are grown on a band of loam (locally called Rutherglen loam) on the lower slopes of the gentle local hills." fact="Fortified wines are grown on a band of loam on the lower slopes of the gentle local hills." varietal1="Muscat" varietaltext1="Explosively rich and sweet, the finish of these wines is cleansing and does not cloy or seem as sweet as the plum pudding flavours of the mid palate suggest. A great winter aperitif and an after-dinner wine at any time of year." varietal2="Fortified Aged White" varietaltext2="It has an intense varietal aroma and flavour that is akin to a mixture of cold tea and fish oil (in the best possible sense). Toffee and butterscotch are also commonly used descriptors for a wine which has more grace and complexity than the all-powerful Muscat." varietal3="" varietaltext3="" varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="53" name="Strathbogie Ranges" blurb="" images="" climate="The altitude of the vineyards ranges from 150 to 650 metres, offering a diversity of climates, though the wines are generally crisp, fresh and deliciously aromatic." date="The region's modern wine history dates from the mid 1970s; since then vineyard development has proceeded at a fairly cautious pace." soil="The vineyards are generally situated on alluvial/colluvial sands and sandy loams composed of decomposed granite that is rather acidic (pH 4-5)." fact="The Strathbogie Ranges are a distinct region, rising high above the surrounding Goulburn and Broken Valleys." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Due to the region's altitude, these are elegant, cool-area wines with melon and lime aromas and flavours. On the palate good acidity means the wines mature quite well over the two to three-year medium term, developing more complex stone fruit flavours." varietal2="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext2="The fresh herbaceous characters of this variety are a hallmark of wines from the Ranges." varietal3="Pinot Noir" varietaltext3="Pinot Noir from the region shows good colour and often shows ripe strawberry traits on nose and palate. At higher elevation the variety can display its traditional delicacy, fine aromas and flavours." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="The region's Shiraz wines are typically excellent, full-fruited styles with spicy berry aromas. The wines show elegance and style, achieving a balance between warm and cool climate styles." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="54" name="Sunbury" blurb="" images="" climate="A cool, dry climate producing elegant wines." date="Sunbury, near Melbourne, is one of Victoria's oldest wine regions, having produced wine since the 1860s." soil="The soils are typically dark and, except on the old alluvial river terraces, not particularly fertile. Their depth and structure varies significantly from lower level plains to hillsides." fact="The region includes deep valleys, grasslands and rolling hills." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The style is elegant with good natural acidity. With a touch of elegance, the resulting wines are not dissimilar to those of Geelong, a region with which Sunbury has much in common." varietal2="Semillon" varietaltext2="Producing warmer, drier vintages that combine varietal flavour with full mouthfeel." varietal3="Shiraz" varietaltext3="Black pepper, spice and black cherry aromas and flavours. Producing medium bodied, and deceptively light Shiraz the alcohol level is rarely higher than 12.5&amp;deg; and the tannins are typically soft and fine." varietal4="Cabernet Franc" varietaltext4="The more common variety in the region is Cabernet Sauvignon, but the performance of each variety suggests that in most vintages it is too cold for Cabernet Sauvignon and that Cabernet Franc is better suited here." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="55" name="Swan Hill" blurb="" images="" climate="The region straddles the Murray River. Swan Hill is an undeniably hot region, though marginally cooler than Murray Darling and with a slightly higher annual rainfall." date="Swan Hill was discovered and named in 1836 by the Surveyor-General of New South Wales, Major Thomas Mitchell, who had camped by the River Murray and spent a noisy night disturbed by flocks of black swans." soil="Soil is red-brown loamy sand." fact="The region's first winery was built in 1930 and is still operating." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="This wine has a soft, melony, peachy easy-to-drink style to be consumed generally within two years of vintage or soon afterwards." varietal2="Shiraz" varietaltext2="These are smooth, medium-bodied fruity reds are usually best drunk within two years." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="The region produces Cabernet of great colour with an attractive mix of berry aromas and a medium-weight, berry-flavoured palate." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="56" name="Upper Goulburn" blurb="" images="" climate="The Upper Goulburn wine region is one of Victoria's coolest regions - The climate is strongly influenced by altitude (300 -700 metres)." date="Grapes have been grown in Upper Goulburn since the 1960s, when the Ritchie family planted grapes at their Delatite property." soil="The soils are varied and range from granitic and granodiorite to sandstone, siltstone, claystone, limestone and dolomite." fact="As in all high country, site selection is of paramount importance, with elevation a key factor in determining style. " varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The wines have considerable weight and richness, while still showing flavours in the stone fruit, nectarine, citrus and melon spectrum and can be long-lived." varietal2="Riesling" varietaltext2="Superbly aromatic, crisp and elegant wines." varietal3="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext3="Tangy, crisp herbal wines that are seldom rich or particularly complex, and good varietal character." varietal4="Cabernet Merlot and Malbec" varietaltext4="Can exhibit eucalypt mint and green leaf characteristics are minimised." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="57" name="Yarra Valley" blurb="" images="" climate="The Yarra Valley is recognised as one of Australia's foremost cool climate regions, capable of making classic styles from a wide range of varieties." date="Vines were first planted in 1838 and viticulture spread rapidly through the 1860s and 1870s. However, increased demand for fortified wine saw Yarra Valley wine production cease in 1921. Replanting began in the late 1960s and by the early 1990s the area under vine passed the high point of the 19th century." soil="Soil ranges from sandy clay loam to well-drained volcanic red." fact="The Yarra Valley was Victoria's first wine growing district, it is known as the birthplace of Victoria's wine industry." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Distinctive regional melon, fig and white peach flavour profiles with diversity in weight, texture and richness that reflects vintage variation and differing winemaking philosophies/techniques." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="The wines are often elegant and can vary from light-bodied through to full-bodied. Despite the smoothness of the tannins, the wines do have a good ability to age." varietal3="Pinot Noir" varietaltext3="Yarra Valley Pinot Noir has a delicacy and surprising length of flavour with  strawberry plum spectrum of fruit flavours." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="Appropriate site selection is critical. The warm, north-facing slopes are highly desirable and capable of producing intensely coloured and flavoured wines, redolent of black cherry spice and pepper." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region></state><state id="4" name="South Australia" ><region id="1" name="Adelaide Hills" blurb="" images="" climate="The cooler climate of the Adelaide Hills defines the region, offering distinct point of difference to many other regions in South Australia." date="Vines were first planted in the region in 1839. " soil="The soils are predominantly grey to grey-brown loamy sands of low to moderate fertility." fact="The main viticultural hazard is the misty, wet weather which often prevails during flowering and results in poor fruit set." varietal1="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext1="Typically the wines are fresh, fragrant and aromatic, yet crisp and food friendly with the distinctive acidity and fine structure that typifies many wine styles from the Hills." varietal2="Chardonnay" varietaltext2="Complex but elegant wines can be expected. The natural levels of acidity are good, allowing makers to use malolactic fermentation to increase complexity without threatening the longevity of the wines or permitting them to become soft and flabby." varietal3="Riesling" varietaltext3="Riesling is grown across the span of climatic sites within the Adelaide Hills, producing razor-sharp, fine and delicate wines in the cooler locations and richer, more conventional wine styles on the warmer sites. For those prepared to wait five to ten years, the cooler sites provide wines with better potential for ageing." varietal4="Pinot Noir" varietaltext4="Pinot Noir asserts itself as a wine style with tremendous potential for the region." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="2" name="Adelaide Plains" blurb="" images="" climate="Dry yet maritime climate with a very low incidence of disease. The region is hot and arid, with an annual rainfall among the lowest of any Australian wine region." date="The first vines were planted in the region in early 1900s." soil="Common soil type is sandy loam." fact="The Adelaide Plains run due north of the city of Adelaide, north-west of the Adelaide Hills and west-south-west of the Barossa Valley." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Most of the Chardonnay produces wine of a medium to full-bodied style, with tropical fruit and ripe peach flavours." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="A medium to full-bodied, forward, ripe style Cabernet Sauvignon which is often blended with Shiraz or Merlot." varietal3="Colombard" varietaltext3="This variety is particularly suited to hot climates, thanks to its ability to retain relatively high levels of natural acidity. For this reason it is much prized as a blend component. Here, however, Colombard can produce a wine with an appearance and flavour profile similar to that of Sauvignon Blanc." varietal4="Chardonnay" varietaltext4="Showing a totally unexpected touch of spice that is normally reserved for cooler climates. Winemaking skills have no doubt played a part, but it demonstrates what can be achieved with grapes grown on mature vines and with controlled yields." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="3" name="Barossa Valley" blurb="" images="" climate="The region has a Mediterranean climate ideal for full-bodied red wines, excellent fortified wines and generally robust white wines. The climate ranges from warm on the valley floor to cool at the higher altitudes in the hills surrounding the Valley." date="A rich winemaking and grape growing heritage dating back to 1842, and a profound and unique Silesian (German) influence." soil="The soils vary widely, but fall in a family of relatively low-fertility clay loam through to more sandy soils, ranging through grey to brown to red." fact="The region is a unique and precious resource, home to some of the oldest vines in the world." varietal1="Shiraz" varietaltext1="Shiraz is recognized universally as the Barossa Valleys signature wine. The wines are lush, velvety and mouth-filling. The flavours range from black cherries to blackberries and the tannins are generally ripe and soft. Many of the wines have great ageing potential." varietal2="Semillon" varietaltext2="Modern day Barossa Semillons are earlier-picked than their old fashioned counterparts. They are also fermented in stainless steel to produce wines of freshness, balance and clear varietal character." varietal3="Grenache and Mourvedre" varietaltext3="Grenache is often blended with Shiraz and Mourvedre, but is also presented as a varietal in its own distinctive right. The wines are often juicy and savoury, with dark cherry and hedge-row fruit characters which appeal to a wide range of palates." varietal4="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext4="Performs best on cooler sites and in moderately cool vintages. French oak is often used to great effect and the overall style is more restrained and firmer than that of Shiraz." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="4" name="Clare Valley" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate features a warm to hot summer, but cooling afternoon breezes play a major role in slowing down the ripening process.  Overall the climate is moderately Continental, with cool to cold nights and warm to hot summer days." date="Clare Valley was settled in the late 1830s, with the first vineyards planted and wines produced in the early 1840s." soil="Soils of the Clare Valley range from classic terra rossa red topsoil over limestone in the Watervale district to the broken slate of Polish Hill River." fact="Situated in the northern Mt Lofty Ranges." varietal1="Riesling" varietaltext1="The Clare Valley is renowned as a premier producer of dry Riesling styles. The wines are characterized by juicy citrus characters, minerality and long, fine natural acidity. The best examples have been proven to age for 20-plus years." varietal2="Shiraz" varietaltext2="The Clare Valley produces Shiraz that has fragrance, power, structure and finesse. Typical fruit characteristics are red berries, spice and chocolate. The wines are underpinned by powerful yet soft tannins and the best examples have long cellaring potential." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="The Clare Valley makes a distinctive regional style of Cabernet with dark berries, chocolate, a juicy mid-palate, cigar box and long fine tannins being typical characters." varietal4="Semillon" varietaltext4="Semillon grown in Clare shows lemon and/or tropical fruit characters. The wines have good fruit concentration and are rich in character with juicy acidity. The best examples can develop further richness with time in bottle." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="5" name="Coonawarra" blurb="" images="" climate="The region is only 100 kilometres (60 miles) inland, and is exposed to a maritime climate, with dry and moderately cool summers." date="Vines were first planted in the Coonawarra region in 1890." soil="The famous terra rossa soil is situated on a slight but all-important limestone ridge." fact="The Coonawarra region is located in the far south-east of South Australia." varietal1="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext1="Coonawarra produces some of Australia's finest Cabernet Sauvignon. The fruit flavours are very concentrated and luscious, covering a broad spectrum from black currant to plum to red cherry to prunes." varietal2="Shiraz" varietaltext2="Coonawarra Shiraz produces medium bodied wines exhibiting pepper and spice fruit characters.  There are many fine examples of shiraz, both as straight varietals and blends with Cabernet Sauvignon." varietal3="Chardonnay" varietaltext3="With its vineyards situated on predominantly limestone, Coonawarra seems highly suited to this variety and, indeed, produces table wine of great quality and longevity." varietal4="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext4="The fragrant, flowery and appealingly fruity style is increasingly gaining recognition." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="6" name="Currency Creek " blurb="" images="" climate="Strong maritime climate, influenced by the surrounding ocean." date="Captain Charles Sturt first explored this region when he travelled down the Murray River in 1829-30 and made his last campsite near what is now the town of Goolwa. Viticulture commenced in the region in 1969." soil="The dominant soil type is sandy slopes overlaying friable cracking clay." fact="Currency Creek is adjacent to the Southern Fleurieu wine region." varietal1="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext1="The wines have delicacy and freshness, with great varietal definition." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="A variety ideally suited to the temperate, mild climate of the region, producing complete and rounded wines with clear varietal definition. As the level of ripeness increases, the flavours move from coffee to blackberry and on to black currant at optimum ripeness." varietal3="Shiraz" varietaltext3="This wine is renowned for lifted aromas that lead into medium-bodied, Rhone Valley-like spicy fruit flavours. This is supported by tannins with elegance and finesse." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="7" name="Eden Valley" blurb="" images="" climate="Overall growing season temperatures are significantly lower than those of the Barossa Valley, and the final stages of ripening and harvesting take place in much cooler conditions." date="With a wine making history dating back to 1847, Eden Valley is home to some of the world's oldest Shiraz and Riesling vineyards." soil="Soils range from sandy loam, to clay loam littered with gravel." fact="The region neighbours the Barossa Valley." varietal1="Riesling" varietaltext1="The Eden Valley also has a proud Riesling tradition and is the most important white grape of the region. The wines have strong lime juice aromas with great intensity of flavour on the palate. As the wines age, marmalade and toasty nuances appear on nose and palate." varietal2="Shiraz" varietaltext2="The wines rarely show the spicy and peppery characters of cool climate Shiraz from other parts of southern Australia. They tend to more luscious plum and blackberry fruit characters, with touches of liquorice and more gamey, forest characters. Structurally, the wines are very smooth, with ripe tannins that are integrated and well balanced, guaranteeing a long life." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="With perfectly ripened cassis-accented fruit flavours. These contrast with wine from higher, cooler sites that have more elegant undertones of green leaf and dark berry characters." varietal4="Chardonnay" varietaltext4="The flavours range through a classic array of melon, fig and cashew." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="8" name="Kangaroo Island " blurb="" images="" climate="A wholly maritime climate prevails, with south-easterly winds blowing directly from the Southern Ocean and prevalent during the growing season, especially from December to March." date="Viticulture in the region commenced in the mid 1980s." soil="Soils vary from sandy, to loam and clay over limestone." fact="Site selection is important, with north and north-east facing sites preferred for viticulture, with protection from the prevailing south-easterly winds a major consideration." varietal1="Red Wines" varietaltext1="Cabernet Sauvignon blended with Merlot has produced some delightful and regionally distinct examples. Shiraz is another quality wine style." varietal2="" varietaltext2="" varietal3="" varietaltext3="" varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="9" name="Langhorne Creek " blurb="" images="" climate="The growing season climate is predominantly shaped by the onshore southerly winds blowing directly from the Southern Ocean across Lake Alexandrina." date="Langhorne Creek was established as a wine growing region in 1860. Langhorne Creek is one of Australia's oldest wine regions." soil="Langhorne Creek's fertile soils are predominantly deep, alluvial sandy loams." fact="The region is nestled among gum trees on the Bremer and Angas rivers." varietal1="Cabernet Sauvignon and Blends" varietaltext1="Flavours are in the red berry spectrum, often with gentle minty and chocolate overtones. Malbec adds a dimension when added to the blend, providing a juicy wine with loads of cassis and dark berry flavours." varietal2="Shiraz and Blends" varietaltext2="Shiraz produces strikingly fruity wines with flavours/aromas of cherry and mint and finishes with a hint of spice." varietal3="" varietaltext3="" varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="10" name="McLaren Vale" blurb="" images="" climate="There is substantial climatic variation throughout McLaren Vale, due to varying exposure to the cooling influence of the nearby ocean. " date="McLaren Vale is one of South Australia's oldest regions, John Reynell established Chateau Reynella in 1838." soil="There is a wide variety of soil types, a reflection of the varied terrain, details of which the region has captured in the world's most comprehensive geological survey of a wine region. The map detailing the enlightening findings is available in most cellar doors." fact="There are also significant changes in altitude as the region merges with the Adelaide Hills to the East and the Fleurieu Peninsula to the South." varietal1="Shiraz" varietaltext1="Generous, textured and complex, McLaren Vale Shiraz combines intense fruit flavours with unique savoury characters." varietal2="Grenache" varietaltext2="The older plantings of bush vines produce incredibly richly flavoured wines, with an almost juicy sweetness." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="The opulent Cabernet Sauvignon of McLaren Vale displays varietal character and layers of flavour." varietal4="Other Varieties" varietaltext4="The climatic diversity has helped McLaren Vale producers to embrace varieties such as Barbera, Fiano, Tempranillo and Mourvedre, and varieties like Viognier, Sangiovese, Zinfandel and Verdelho." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="11" name="Mount Benson " blurb="" images="" climate="Strongly influenced by the Southern Ocean, the climate in Mount Benson is cool and maritime.  Spring frost is the chief viticultural hazard." date="Viticulture is new to the region, commencing in 1989." soil="Irrigation is provided by high quality ground water, which exists in abundance in the underlying limestone." fact="The Mount Benson region is located along the South Australian coastline in close proximity to the Coonawarra, Wrattonbully and Padthaway wine regions." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Chardonnay is fine and elegant and has an excellent intensity." varietal2="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext2="These crisp, grassy, herbaceous wines can have attractive touches of gooseberry and passionfruit." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon and Merlot" varietaltext3="Natural tannin levels are good, and the overall extract and weight are more than satisfactory." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="Cherry, black pepper and spice flavours in a medium-bodied frame lending itself to the use of French oak." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="12" name="Mount Gambier" blurb="" images="" climate="The Mount Gambier region is generally regarded as having a Mediterranean climate, characterized by warm to hot, dry summers and mild to cool winters where most rain usually falls." date="The Mount Gambier region has been established as a viticultural region since 1982." soil="The Mount Gambier region is underlain by sedimentary limestone with igneous rocks scattered through the region from volcanic activity. In the vicinity of the volcanic cones, the ash has weathered into a well drained, highly fertile loam which is highly regarded for primary production." fact="Located midway between Melbourne and Adelaide, the Mount Gambier wine region occupies the southernmost area of South Australia." varietal1="Pinot Noir" varietaltext1="Ripe berries and spicy, sweet fruit notes with the ability to retain sappy freshness with age." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="Cabernets of this region are juicy, fresh and perfumed." varietal3="Chardonnay" varietaltext3="Nicely shaped with lemony, grapefruit and melon notes." varietal4="Riesling" varietaltext4="Floral and citrus notes, punchy acidity and hints of grapefruit and crisp apple." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="13" name="Padthaway" blurb="" images="" climate="A maritime climate prevails. Chief viticultural hazard is spring frost." date="Identified as a potential wine region by a scientific study in 1963." soil="Soil is brown, sandy loam over red-brown clay over limestone." fact="Padthaway is in the south-east of South Australia." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Historically Chardonnay has been recognised as the most successful of the wines from Padthaway. There is a particular regional character to the fruit flavour which is strongly reminiscent of grapefruit. Other flavours include conventional notes of melon, fig and white peach." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="Released either as a single varietal or blended with Merlot, the wine is typically of medium body with cool climate characteristics to the fore. The tannins are fine and soft and the wine does not need significant oak influence. The wines are approachable young but have the potential to age for many years." varietal3="Pinot Noir" varietaltext3="This wine is as temperamental in Padthaway as in any other region." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="14" name="Riverland" blurb="" images="" climate="The Riverland climate is Continental, resulting in long sunny days and noticeably cooler nights." date="" soil="The soils of the Riverland vary significantly. The two main types are river valley soils, consisting of sandy loams over clay subsoils, and Mallee soils on higher ground, consisting of wind-blown sands over lime and clay layers." fact="Set within a panoramic backdrop of limestone cliffs, with their layers of colour and texture, the Riverland follows the twists and turns of the Murray as it rolls toward the Ocean." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Riverland Chardonnay often exhibits vivacious and ripe flavours. Oak is often used, and this supports the richness of the wines as well as adding further complexity." varietal2="Shiraz" varietaltext2="It responds well to the region's conditions and the resulting wines are often very approachable. Dark berries and plums are terms commonly used to describe the scent of Riverland Shiraz." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon and Merlot" varietaltext3="Each is used as single varietal wines and in blends. The region's warm temperatures tend to bring out the richer raspberry characteristics in the wines, while in cooler years the overall profile can demonstrate mint and blackcurrant." varietal4="Alternative varietals" varietaltext4="From Arneis to Zinfandel, delivering high-quality and delicious wines." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="15" name="Robe" blurb="" images="" climate="The soils, aspect and protected maritime climate lead to the production of powerful yet elegant wines." date="Vineyard development began to flourish in the mid to late 1990s." soil="Robe has a wide variety of soil types, ranging from terra rossa and sandy loam on the limestone ridges to calcareous sand on the coastal dunes and rendzinas on the coastal plains." fact="Located on an unspoilt, rugged coastal landscape nestled between lakes and the Southern Ocean on South Australia's Limestone Coast. It is situated between the townships of Robe and Beachport and is south of the Mount Benson wine region." varietal1="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext1="The wine has punchy tropical and grassy aromas and these aromas are underpinned by a palate that is pure, crisp and flavoursome." varietal2="Chardonnay" varietaltext2="Offers fragrant citrus and apple aromas with rich, elegant citrus and mineral flavours. Balanced natural acidity gives the wines finesse and structure." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="The wine has varietal aromas of blackberry, tobacco and mint. The palate has good structure and texture with sweet ripe fruit characters. This variety seems to be well suited to Robe's maritime climate." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="Robe Shiraz is complex with intense raspberries, mulberries and black pepper aromas. The wines have rich elegant berry fruit and a succulent mid palate that is framed by fine tannins. Balanced acidity offering a long spicy finish." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="16" name="Southern Fleurieu" blurb="" images="" climate="Mediterranean climate, strongly influenced by the surrounding ocean." date="" soil="The region's soils are suited to viticulture and support moderately vigorous vine growth. Major soil types are sandy loam and buckshot gravel both over limestone subsoil." fact="The Southern Fleurieu is less than an hours' drive south of Adelaide." varietal1="Riesling" varietaltext1="Made in dry and semi-dry style Riesling is crisp and tasty when made in a dry style but also performs awell when made in a sweeter style." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="In the warmer years the region produces a wine with a most attractive mix of gently herbaceous and tobacco characters, with sweeter red and blackberry flavours. The tannins are fine and supple, and the wine is medium bodied." varietal3="Merlot" varietaltext3="This wine is sometimes made as a straight varietal and at other time blended with Cabernet Sauvignon. The variety appears particularly well suited to the climate and soil of the Peninsula, producing wines of vibrant varietal character. The flavours run through a spectrum of leaf, mint and red berry, with a fragrant bouquet." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="17" name="Southern Flinders Rangers" blurb="" images="" climate="Climate is warm and dry with maritime influences from Spencer Gulf." date="Viticulture emerged in the 1980s." soil="The soils, although varied, are quite deep and mostly limestone based, fertile and quite suitable for viticulture." fact="The region is a natural north-western extension of the Clare Valley, with which it shares many geological factors." varietal1="Shiraz" varietaltext1="These are full-coloured, robust reds with rich berry and liquorice aromas that bear some resemblance to those of the Clare Valley. The wines have good ageing potential." varietal2="" varietaltext2="" varietal3="" varietaltext3="" varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="18" name="Warattonbully" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate is in between that of its neighbours, Coonawarra and Padthaway." date="The first vines for grapes were planted in the late 1960s, but it was not until the 1990s on the excellent soils and elevated sites which attracted many winemakers from surrounding areas." soil="The Wrattonbully wine region in the Limestone Coast of South Australia comprises ancient and mineral rich geology dating back to the Miocene period around 10-30 million years ago.  Inland maritime climate." fact="Wrattonbully is an appellation within the Limestone Coast, located between the wine regions of Padthaway and the Coonawarra." varietal1="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext1="It produces fruit flavours of dark berries and intense black currents and has firm tannins." varietal2="Shiraz" varietaltext2="Medium to full bodied spectrum and intense aromatics with spice, pepper and liquorice." varietal3="Merlot" varietaltext3="The Merlot produced is soft, rich and fruit driven, with good power, flavour, deep colour and exceptional tannin structure." varietal4="Chardonnay" varietaltext4="Chardonnay is of great character and juicy lemon flavour, with good acid structure." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region></state><state id="5" name="Western Australia" ><region id="58" name="Blackwood Valley" blurb="" images="" climate="Dry summers, cold wet winters - winter frosts sometimes extending into the spring." date="Since 1976 this region has increasingly taken advantage of its favourable soils and climactic conditions to produce wines of class and distinction." soil="The soils are part of the Darling Plateau system, with moderately incised valleys providing gravel and gravelly soils, yellow soils and red earths." fact="The region is situated on the same latitude as Margaret River and shares many of the same basic climatic characteristics." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The style is generous and rich, with ripe melon and peach fruit flavours." varietal2="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext2="The cooler climate suits this popular varietal well. The wines show well the grassy, vegetal flavours that are typical of the variety." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="Blackcurrant and dark chocolate characters. These are supported by long, fine tannins, giving the wines excellent aging potential." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="A mix of sweet, round fruit and touches of pepper and spice." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="59" name="Geographe" blurb="" images="" climate="A compact region unified by its warm to hot and mostly maritime-influenced climate - summers are dry but rainfall is generous during winter and relative humidity is quite high." date="Formally established as a region in 1999." soil="The coastal tuart sands have limestone as their parent material and overlie limestone." fact="In this region, excessively warm temperatures are modified by the prevailing south-west sea breezes coming off the Indian Ocean. Summers are dry but rainfall is generous during winter and relative humidity is quite high." varietal1="Shiraz" varietaltext1="The styles vary substantially, from the robust to softer and more elegant styles, but each with a core of cherry and mint fruit." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext2="Whether blended with Merlot or not, Cabernet Sauvignon tends to be delicate with lingering, soft fine-grained tannins." varietal3="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext3="The cooler sites produce wines with intense citrus and grass characters, while the warmer sites veer through melon and guava fruits." varietal4="Semillon" varietaltext4="Crisp tangy wine with grassy herbal overtones; a light touch of oak is an optional extra." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="60" name="Great Southern" blurb="" images="" climate="The climatic conditions range from maritime-influenced to Continental. Rainfall and humidity increase to the south of the region and temperature significantly increases inland, towards the north." date="The region was instrumental in the establishment of modern winemaking in Western Australia in the 1960s." soil="Soils are mainly either lateritic gravelly sandy loams or sandy loams deriving directly from granite and gneissic bedrocks. Fertility is moderate, as are typical yields." fact="Great Southern is aptly named, as it is pounded by the Southern Ocean and is steeped in the history of early European settlement." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="Elegant, tightly structured, grapefruit-accented Chardonnay which ages well is produced in the region. Wines of the south can be a little finer and softer while those of the north are slightly more powerful." varietal2="Riesling" varietaltext2="The wines age superbly, seldom reaching the peak of their development in less than ten years. As well as being crisp and lean in youth, the wines still have intense flavour, typically in the citrus spectrum with an underlay of herbs." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="Deep colour, intense flavour and powerful structure. They have classic Cabernet sensibilities with an austerity of flavours." varietal4="Pinot Noir" varietaltext4="Some exciting wines have appeared from this region in slightly cooler years." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="61" name="Manjimup" blurb="" images="" climate="The climate is influenced by the Indian and the Southern oceans. Cold winters provide true vine dormancy, while plentiful spring rainfall promotes good budburst and early growth." date="Manjimup's viticulture and wine foundation began with research in the mid-1970s that identified the area for its potential as a leading grape growing region." soil="The dividing line with Pemberton is largely based on soil type, topography and elevation. Soil is predominantly red gravelly loam." fact="Located in the heart of Western Australia's south-west among towering forests, Manjimup is situated immediately north of the Pemberton region." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The wines are elegant, light to medium-bodied, with the melon, citrus flavours of cooler grown Chardonnay. As the vines mature it will bring increased structure and intensity to the wines." varietal2="Verdelho" varietaltext2="This wine has great freshness and zingy acidity here, yet it retains its tropical flavours and rounded mouthfeel." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon and Merlot" varietaltext3="Dr John Gladstone has observed that both mean temperatures and sunshine hours are very close to those of Bordeaux. It is thus no surprise to find that some very appealing and elegant Cabernet Merlot blends have been produced." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="62" name="Margaret River" blurb="" images="" climate="Margaret River's climate is strongly maritime-influenced, as might be expected in a region surrounded by the ocean on three sides." date="The region was 'discovered' in the early 1970s after various pieces of research from Professor Harold Olmo and Dr John Gladstones identified it as a potentially great grape growing region." soil="The principal soil type is gravelly sandy loam that has formed directly from the underlying granite and gneissic rock." fact="Located approximately three hours' drive south of Perth, Margaret River is located in the far south-west corner of Western Australia and is one of the most geographically isolated and pure wine regions in the world." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The voluptuous fruit lends itself to the full range of winemaking techniques." varietal2="Sauvignon Blanc and Semillon" varietaltext2="The Semillon has a pleasantly herbal cut grass character which can blend seamlessly with the Sauvignon Blanc." varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="The style has evolved the common threads are ripe grapes that provide a sweet core to all the wines, which are never leafy or herbal, and often with slightly earthy or gravelly tannins. These latter characteristics are very much a product of the local terroir, which provides complexity, authority and structure." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="Various styles can be present with everything from medium bodied spice and pepper to rich full bodied fruit driven wines available." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="63" name="Peel" blurb="" images="" climate="This coastal region has a Mediterranean climate with cool, wet winters and hot dry summers. Soils range from granite and gravel soils to limestone sands and fluvial sediments." date="The first vines were planted in the region in 1857. Modern day viticulture commenced in the mid 1970s." soil="The eastern extension of the Peel region includes very old granite and gravel soils. These soils are totally different to the limestone sands and fluvial sediments of the coastal area, which have significant ground-water reserves three to 15 metres (49 feet) below the surface." fact="The European settlement of Peel dates back to 1829 when a visionary named Thomas Peel brought three ships of migrants from England for the Peel Settlement Scheme." varietal1="Chenin Blanc" varietaltext1="This was the first white grape to be planted in Peel. The wine is produced with or without oak and gains character and depth with short to medium-term cellaring." varietal2="Chardonnay" varietaltext2="Character notes range from melon and stone fruit to rich and buttery" varietal3="Cabernet Sauvignon" varietaltext3="Producing a medium-bodied wine, Cabernet is slightly firmer when grown inland at higher elevations." varietal4="Shiraz" varietaltext4="The style is medium-bodied with sweet, fine, ripe tannins." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="64" name="Pemberton" blurb="" images="" climate="Pemberton is cooler than neighbouring Manjimup, with fewer sunshine hours, more rainfall except in January and February and greater relative humidity." date="Pemberton was first planted experimentally in 1977, with commercial vineyards following in 1982." soil="There are two major soil types: lateritic gravelly sands / gravelly loams and the more fertile karri loam." fact="Situated in the lower south-west of Western Australia, west of the Great Southern and south-east of the Margaret River regions. A region rich in flora, forests of karri trees abound." varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="It produces opulently flavoured and structured wines, with an almost creamy texture. These wines respond well to the generous use of high-quality French oak." varietal2="Merlot" varietaltext2="Either as a varietal in its own right, or blended with Cabernet Sauvignon, Merlot impresses, with good varietal character and mouth feel." varietal3="Pinot Noir" varietaltext3="Ripe berry notes, light and layered with flavour, the nuances of which will further develop with time. Primary fruit characters include raspberries and cherries and the wine is balanced with fine tannins in the finish." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="65" name="Perth Hills" blurb="" images="" climate="Rivulets and often dry creek beds, ridges, hills and valleys criss-cross the region in every direction, offering an almost unlimited choice of aspect and slope, but those cut off from the sea breeze influence tend to be warmer rather than cooler." date="The first vineyard was planted in Darlington in the 1880s, followed by a second in Glen Forrest in 1896." soil="Soil ranges from ironstone and gravel sandy loams as well as gravelly loams which overlay clay." fact="The earliest of the present day wineries in the region date back to the mid 1970s. 	The region is approximately 30 minutes drive east of Perth. " varietal1="Chardonnay" varietaltext1="The style of these wines is generous, bursting with ripe melon and peach characters." varietal2="Cabernet Sauvignon and Merlot" varietaltext2="The wines are reliable and pleasant; full flavoured, with chocolate, earthy and berry flavours." varietal3="Shiraz" varietaltext3="Shiraz from this region as in other warmer regions is generously fruit driven." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region><region id="66" name="Swan District" blurb="" images="" climate="Warm to hot Mediterranean climate, very dry during ripening and harvest. Cool sea breezes provide relief from the heat." date="The Swan District is Western Australia's oldest wine region, having been planted by English settlers soon after their arrival in 1829." soil="The soils of the Swan District are typically young alluvial soils; very deep, with excellent moisture retention capacity." fact="For almost 150 years it was the only significant wine-producing region in Western Australia, and produced fortified wines for much of its first 100 years." varietal1="Chenin Blanc" varietaltext1="In this climate the wine produced has a certain luscious richness, which responds well to bottle age, producing a full-flavoured white of voluptuous dimensions." varietal2="Chardonnay" varietaltext2="Buttery, peachy wines from this grape." varietal3="Verdelho" varietaltext3="Rich honeyed, honeysuckle flavours." varietal4="" varietaltext4="" credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region></state><state id="6" name="Northern Territory" ></state><state id="7" name="Tasmania" ><region id="36" name="Tasmania" blurb="" images="" climate="Tasmania has a moderate maritime climate, cooled by prevailing westerlies off the Southern Ocean, providing conditions that are generally free from extremes. Significant climatic diversity is evident among the viticultural areas and dolerite-capped mountains shelter many of the state's vineyards from high winds and heavy rainfall." date="Tasmania has a long viticultural history with records dating from 1823." soil="The Tasmanian landscape is dominated by dolerite-capped mountains that shelter the state's vineyards from high winds and rainfall. On the lower slopes, the vineyard soils are formed from ancient sandstones and mudstones and also from more recent river sediments and igneous rock of volcanic origin." fact="Tasmania is one zone, but has seven wine growing areas - Tamar Valley and the North East areas in the north, the East Coast, the North West and the Derwent Valley, Coal River Valley and Huon/Channel areas in the south." varietal1="Sparkling Wine" varietaltext1="Sparkling wines are usually produced in the traditional bottle-fermented method. In Tasmania, fine balance between fruit and acidity is naturally achieved on the vine." varietal2="Pinot Noir" varietaltext2="Tasmanian conditions regularly produce soft, luscious and strongly perfumed wines. The wines range from elegant and fruit driven to complex and gamey." varietal3="Chardonnay" varietaltext3="Because of the cool nature of the climate, extended ripening on the vine allows for greater varietal fruit expression for Chardonnay in Tasmania." varietal4="Sauvignon Blanc" varietaltext4="Extended ripening periods due to the cool Tasmanian climate yields wines of great varietal fruit character." credit1="" credit2="" credit3="" pin="" ></region></state></states>